Barrows Mussey Translations, 1940-[1944?]: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Barrows Mussey Translations
circa 1940-1944
C0009
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
2.1 linear feet 5 archival boxes
Mussey, June Barrows, 1910-1985.
The Barrows Mussey Translations collection consists of English translations of works by various European authors, predominately German, made by the American translator Barrows Mussey.
Barrows Mussey was an American translator who completed English translations of various works, mostly novels, of German and other European authors during the 1940s.
Consists of typed manuscripts, often heavily revised or corrected, of Mussey's English translations of various works, mostly novels, of German and other European authors during the 1940s. Included are Frans G. Bengtsson's Red Orm (incomplete); Hermann Borchardt's The Conspiracy of Carpenters; Dola de Jong's Knikkernik, Knakkernak, and Knokkernok (several chapters); Anthony Fokker and Frank Harper's Specialized in Terror; Heinrich Hauser's Time Was; Frederick Heydenau's The Wrath of the Eagles; Hugo von Hofmannsthal's Plays at Salzburg; Hermann Kesten's Colonel Kock; Christine Liungman's The Shining Sea; Ernst Lothar's Beneath Another Sun and A Woman is Witness; Emil Ludwig's Mediterranean; Gerardo E. Neisser's Call Me Frank; and Hermann Rauschning's The Redemption of Democracy.
In addition, the collection includes Fritz von Unruh's untitled 1941 novel, as well as Franz Werfel's Jacobowsky and the Colonel and A Portrait of Giuseppe Verdi. Some of Mussey's translations were apparently never published. "Translators and Traitors," Mussey's article describing his experiences as a translator, rounds out the collection.
The following standard abbreviation, or its variations, is used to identify materials in this collection: ALS = autograph letter signed, TLS = typed letter signed, TMs = typed manuscript, TMsS = typed manuscript signed.
The collection is arranged alphabetically by author name.
Collection is open for research use.
Originally, this collection formed part of Princeton's Archives of American Literature.
No appraisal information is available.
Some of the manuscripts found in draft form in the collection came to print in the following publications: Bengtsson, Frans G., Red Orm (NY: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1943); Borchardt, Hermann, The Conspiracy of Carpenters (NY: Simon and Schuster, 1943); De Jong, Dola, Knikkernik, Knakkernak, and Knokkernok (NY: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1942); Hauser, Heinrich, Time Was (NY: Reynal & Hitchcock, 1942); Lothar, Ernst, Beneath Another Sun (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, Doran, 1943), and A Woman is Witness (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, Doran, 1941); Ludwig, Emil, The Mediterranean (NY: Whittlesey House, 1942); and Rauschning, Hermann, The Redemption Of Democracy (NY: Alliance Book Corp., 1941).
Dutch fiction -- Translations into English.; German fiction -- Translations into English.; Swedish fiction -- Translations into English.; Translating and interpreting -- United States -- 20th century.; Translators -- United States -- 20th century.; European literature; American literature
- Bengtsson, Franz Gunnar, dates not examined; 1 folder
  - Red Orm (incomplete), dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    - Program: December 24, 1940, Berlin, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- Bochardt, Hermann, 1943 January 14; 3 folders
  - ALS by Bochardt to Mussey, 1943 January 14; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - The Conspiracy of the Carpenters, dates not examined; 3 folders
    - TMs (I), English translation (Simon & Schuster), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - TMs (II), English translation (Simon & Schuster), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - TMs (III), English translation (Simon & Schuster), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
- De Jong, Dola, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - De Herfstfabriek van Kabauter Kleur, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon), Dutch (unpublished), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
      English translation made but lost.
  - Knikkernik Is a Hero, Chapter VII, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon) (Scribner), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Fokker, Anthony and Frank Harper, dates not examined; 1 folder
  - Specialized in Terror, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, German, translation made but lost (unpublished), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
- Hauser, Heinrich, dates not examined; 1 folder
  - Time Was, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- Heydenau, Frederick, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - The Wrath of the Eagles, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (mostly carbon), German: Der Zorn der Adler, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
    - Program: February 22, 194?, Berlin, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Report on Heydenau's Ms, The Wrath of the Eagles, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    - Program: December 25, 1940, Rome, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Hofmannsthal, Hugo von, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - "Festival Plays at Salzburg", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    - Program: December 25, 1940, Berlin, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - "Festpiele in Salzburg", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
    - Program: May 17, 1942, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Kesten, Hermann, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - "Colonel Kock", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, English translation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    - Program: December 25, 1940, Berlin, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - "Oberst Kock", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon), German, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - Program: May 17, 1942, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
- Liungman, Christine, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - The Shining Sea, dates not examined; 2 folders
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
    - TMs (carbon), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
- Lothar, Ernst, 1940-1941; 2 boxes
  - Beneath Another Sun, Part I, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, German, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Beneath Another Sun, Part II, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, German, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Beneath Another Sun, Part I, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, English translation (Doubleday), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Beneath Another Sun, Part II, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs with holograph revisions, English translation (Doubleday), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - 2 ALsS to Barrows Mussey, 1940-1941; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - A Woman is Witness, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon), German, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - A Woman is Witness, Part I, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, English translation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - A Woman is Witness, Part II, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, English translation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Ludwig, Emil, dates not examined; 2 boxes
  - The Mediterranean, Part I, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
      Contains corrections, glossary, new forward (German) for translation
  - The Mediterranean, Part II, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - The Mediterranean, Part III, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 1)
- Mussey, Barrows, dates not examined; 1 folder
  - "Translators and Traitors", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 2)
- Neisser, Gerardo E., 1942; 1 folder
  - "Call Me Frank", dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (carbon), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - TLS by Neisser to Mussey, 1942; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Program: December 25, 1940, London, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 3)
- Rauschning, Hermann, dates not examined; 2 folders
  - Das Jahr der Entscheidung, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs, German (English translation made but lost) (unpublished), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - The Redemption of Democracy, dates not examined; 1 folder
    - TMs (Alliance Book Corp.), dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 5)
- Unruh, Fritz von, 1941; 1 folder
  - [Untitled novel], 1941; 1 folder
    - TMs, English translation, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - TLS by Unruh to Mussey, 1941; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - ALS by Unruh to Mussey, 1941; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- Wertel, Franz, dates not examined; 4 folders
  - Jacobowsky and the Colonel, dates not examined; 2 folders
    - TMs (carbon), German: Jacobowsky und der Oberst, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 7)
    - TMs, English translation by Mussey, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - A Portrait of Giuseppe Verdi, dates not examined; 2 folders
    - TMsS (carbon), German: Ein Bildnis Giuseppe Verdi's, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 9)
    - TMs, English translation by Mussey, dates not examined; 1 folder (Folder 10)
- 32101040795344 (Box 1)
- 32101040795351 (Box 2)
- 32101040795369 (Box 3)
- 32101040795377 (Box 4)
- 32101040795385 (Box 5)